Guide to the Talman Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Talman family papers
1683-1866
MS 662
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box, 1 folio)
Deeds, leases, miscellaneous documents, and some correspondence of the Talman family, early settlers of Guilford, Connecticut.
Talman family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1948.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. General Documents. II. Deeds and Land Transactions.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains papers dating from 1683 to 1866 which pertain to the Talman family, early settlers of Guilford, Connecticut. The papers are divided into two series, the contents of which are arranged alphabetically by author.
The first series, GENERAL DOCUMENTS, contains fourteen items not related to land holdings or transfers. Included are, for instance, a bond for a slave, an apprenticeship agreement, a statement of early 18th-century Puritan religious belief entitled "Doctrine of Faith," inventories, and a few pieces of correspondence.
Series II, DEEDS AND LAND TRANSACTIONS, consists of thirty-three deeds to land in and around Guilford, as well as nine other documents dealing with land transactions. Included are certificates, memoranda, and correspondence concerning land.
These papers were purchased by Yale University in 1948.
Biographical / Historical
Four generations of the Talman family are represented in these papers: Peter Talman (1658-1726) and his wife Anna (Wright) Walstone Talman; their son Ebenezer (1692-1770); their grandchildren Peter III and Sarah (Talman) Curtis; and their great-grandson Peter, Jr., and his wife Ruth. The first Peter, born in Newport, Rhode Island, on March 22, 1658, was a physician who settled in Guilford in 1683. He married Anna Wright in 1683 and died on July 6, 1726. His son, Ebenezer, was also a doctor. (See A History of the Plantation of Menunkatuck and of the Original Town of Guilford, Connecticut by Bernard C. Steiner.)
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Families; Medicine -- Formulae, receipts, prescriptions; Connecticut; Guilford (Conn.) -- History; Deeds; Physicians; Chittenden, Jared; Chittenden, Levi; Newcomer, Caroline Annie Stoddard, 1852-1943; Talman, Anna Wright Walstone, 1693?-1773; Talman, Ebenezer, 1692-1770; Talman, Eli; Talman, Peter, 1658-1726; Talman family
- GENERAL DOCUMENTS, 1683-1866; Series I; .25 linear feet (1 box, 1 folio)
  Scope and Contents
  The Talmans were among the early settlers of Guilford, Connecticut. All the documents in this collection are believed to be connected with this family. The dates of these documents range from 1683-1866.
  The 14 documents in this series are concerned either with legal matters unrelated to land or with no legal affairs at all. Typical documents include a bond for a slave; correspondence that makes no mention of land transactions; an apprenticeship agreement; a paper entitled "Doctrine of Faith," which is a statement of early 18th-century Puritan religious belief.
  - Cook, Mary Ann: A.L.S. to Peter Talman, her brother, 1820 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Curtis, Sarah (Talman): Receipt for her dowry, 1795 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Doctrine of Faith" (Guilford, early 18th century)
    General note
    See: box 2
  - Miscellaneous Remedies of a Dr. Benjamin Brown of N.Y., undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - New Haven Insurance Agency: Form letter to Peter Talman, 1851 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Norton, Joel: Apprenticeship to Ebenezer Talman, 1765 August 6 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Roll, Elizabeth: ALS to Peter Talman, [n.y.] July 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Rossiter, Sherman: ALS to Peter Talman, 1822 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ruggles, Nathanial: Bond to Ebenezer Talman (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Talman Family: Genealogical Data (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Talman, Ebenezer: Bond to Samuel Beecher for E. Talman's re-purchase of a black boy sold to Beecher, 1746 September 17 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Talman, Eli and Peter: Inventories of the furniture of:
    - Catharine Stoddard, 1797 January 16 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Clarissa Slaughter, 1798 December 28 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Perthenia Palmer, 1893 December 10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Terril, Huldah: ALS to Ruth Talman, her sister, 1808 March 11. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Unidentified Writer: ALS to Peter Talman of North Guilford, [n.y.] July 13 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- DEEDS AND LAND TRANSACTIONS, 1683-1866; Series II; .25 linear feet (1 box, 1 folio)
  Deeds & Land Transactions
  The 42 documents in this series consist mainly of 33 deeds. The remaining documents include such items as three certificates for land and a letter that mentions how some land was disposed of in a will. One deed is for land in Branford, Connecticut, but all the other deeds are for land in Guilford and North Guilford.
  - Avered, Josiah: Deed to Ebenezer Talman of Guilford (with Elizabeth his wife), 1722 December 31
    See box 2
  - Beach, Perthenia: Memo to a Mr. Bradley re: her father's estate, 1775 April 16 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Benton, Ebenezer: Deed to Ebenezer Talman of Guilford, 1739/40 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Benton, William J.: Deed to Charles B. Hull of Guilford, 1866 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bungis, Thomas: Deed to Peter Talman IV of Guilford, 1822 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Chapman, Esther: Deed to Peter Talman III of Guilford, 1790 February 16 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Chapman, Israel: Deed to Peter Talman III of Guilford, 1792 January 10 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Chapman, Jonathan: ANS to a sibling (fragment), 1789 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Chittenden, Levi and Jared: Deed for land sold to Peter Talman, 1831 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Clay, Joseph: Deed to Peter Talman of Guilford, 1694 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Collins, Oliver
    - Deed to Ebenezer Talman of Guilford, 1744 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Deed to Peter Talman III of Guilford, 1769 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Deed to Peter Talman III (first half of deed is missing), 1773 March 15 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Cruttenden, John: Deed to Ebenezer Talman of Guilford, 1730 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Evarts, Timothy: Deed to Ebenezer Talman, 1754 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Hill, Michael
    - Deed to Ebenezer Talman of Guilford, 1729/30 January 30 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Deed to Ebenezer Talman, 1729/30 February 6 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Hill, Nathaniel: Certificate for land in the sixth and seventh divisions of Guilford, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Hill, Samuel
    - Deed to Ebenezer Talman of Guilford, 1730/31 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Certificate for land in the sixth division of Guilford, 1744 June 13 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Hoadley, William and Nathaniel Foot: Deed to Peter Talman I, land in Branford, 1708 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Hodgkin, Noah: Deed to Ebenezer Talman of Guilford, 1743 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Hubbard, Samuel
    - Deed to Ruth Talman of Guilford, 1818 November 4 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Deed to Peter Talman of Guilford, 1819 June 9 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Lee, Samuel: Deed to Peter Talman of Guilford, 1711 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Miscellaneous Scraps, 1753 and undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Redfield, John
    - Deed to Peter Talman, Jr., 1804 June 28 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Deed for land sold to Ruth Talman, 1804 June 28 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Rose, Jonathan: Deed to Ebenezer Talman of Guilford, 1755 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Rose, Reuben: Deed to Peter Talman III, 1791 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Rossiter, Jonathan
    - Deed to Peter Talman of Guilford, 1719 September 20 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Deed to Ebenezer Talman of Guilford, 1742/43 March 24 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Rossiter, Josiah: Deed to Peter Talman I, 1695 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Schovel, Abigail: Deed to Peter Talman III. Deed signed by Abigail Schovel, Solomon Spencer, and Unis Spencer, 1790 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Stoddard, Harmon: ALS to Peter Talman, his brother-in-law, 1816 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Stone, William: Deed for Peter Talman in Guilford, 1695 July 22 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Talman, Ebenezer
    - Certificate for land in Guilford, 1744 September 28 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Deed to his son, Peter Talman III, of Guilford, 1765 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Talman, Eli: Deed to Peter Talman, 1804 September 27 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Talman, Peter: Memorandum of land owned by Peter Talman, 1683 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Talman, Peter and Anna: Deed to Ebenezer Talman, 1720 April 12 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Note: Peter and Anna Talman were husband and wife. The Peter Talman of this deed is Peter Talman I.
  - Talman II, Peter: Lease to Ebenezer and Anna Talman, his father and mother, 1766 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Oversize
  This folio contains material from Series I, Folder 3, and from Series II, folder 15.
  - "The Doctrine of Faith" (Guilford, early 18th century) (Box 2)
  - Avered, Josiah: Deed to Ebenezer Talman of Guilford (with Elizabeth his wife), 1722 December 31 (Box 2)